Per G. Stensland Papers
Per G. Stensland Papers
1941-1983
Stensland, Per Gustaf, 1913-
11.75 linear ft.
Per G. Stensland (born in Sweden) was an American educator and consultant. The Per Stensland Papers include conference papers, correspondence, proceedings, reports, and speeches. The papers reflect Stensland’s teaching activities at various institutions, among them, Teacher’s College at Columbia University, the University of Toronto, the University of Saskatchewan, Kansas State College and the Milbank Memorial Fund. There is material related to Stensland’s activities as a member and field representative for the International Council for Adult Education (ICAE). Correspondents whose letters are of greatest depth and duration include James T. Farrell, Margaret Gayfer, Budd L. Hall, J.R. Kidd, George E. Miller, Paul A. Miller, Gunnar Myrdal, Alexander Robinson, and Dorothy Thomas.
149428
Biographical History
Per Stensland, educator, writer and speech-maker, was a native of Sweden. While in Sweden he studied Gunnar Myrdal and Dag Hammarskjold. Very little else is know about his early life at this time.
He eventually came to the United States, where he was on the faculty of several institutions including Kansas State, Texas Technological College, Teacher's College, University of Saskatchewan, New York University, Hunter College, and the University of Toronto. He was a fellow and coordinator of a five year seminar run by the Milbank Memorial Fund. He consulted for World Health Organization, World Bank, European Economic Cooperation (OEEC), Kellogg Foundation, and others. He also represented the International Council of Adult Educators (ICAE) on a number of projects.
His areas of expertise were medical education, particularly community medicine, community development, educational sociology, nursing education, and teaching strategies. He lectured, taught and wrote on all these subjects.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Per G. Stensland Papers documents Stensland's professional career between 1941 and 1983. It includes correspondence, teaching materials, speeches, papers in printed and manuscript format, offprints, conference materials, reports, and newspaper clippings. Stensland led many workshops so the collection also includes correspondence, articles and working papers written by others. A number of the papers are unpublished.
Arrangement of the Collection
The material is arranged chronologically within topics, largely preserving Stensland's original arrangement.
Related Material
The library holds a considerable number of collections related to adult and continuing education. Please refer to for a complete listing. Collections which are particularly relevant include:
International Council for Adult Education (ICAE)
Subject and Genre Headings
Adult education; Farrell, James T. (James Thomas), 1904-1979; Gayfer, Margaret; Hall, Budd L.; Kidd, J. R. (James Robbins), 1915-1982; Miller, George E., b. 1919; Miller, Paul A., 1917-; Myrdal, Gunnar, 1898-1987; Robinson, Alexander; Stensland, Per Gustaf, 1913-, Archives; Thomas, Dorothy; International Council for Adult Education; Milbank Memorial Fund; Adult education; Educators, United States; Correspondence.; Proceedings.; Reports.; Speeches (documents); Educators.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Per G. Stensland
Inventory
- Writings
  - List of selected publications by PGS (Box 1)
  - Community development (Box 1)
  - Adult education (Box 1)
  - Health and nursing (Box 1)
  - Communication (Box 1)
  - General, 5 folders (Box 1)
  - Adult education study (Box 1)
  - Early study and papers (Box 1)
  - Basic ideas in adult education (Box 1)
  - Book reviews, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Manuscript review (Box 1)
- Correspondence
  - General
    - 1963-1967 (Box 1)
    - 1967 (Box 1)
    - 1968 (Box 1)
    - 1969 (Box 1)
    - 1970-1971 (Box 1)
    - 1970-1973 (Box 1)
    - 1971-1973 (Box 1)
    - 1971-1975 (Box 1)
    - 1975-1978 (Box 1)
  - Publications (Box 1)
  - Professional (Box 1)
  - Publication requests (Box 1)
  - Community development Jr. (Box 1)
  - Social sciences and medicine (Box 1)
  - Harvard Business Review (Box 1)
  - Article submissions (Box 1)
  - Backett, Maurice (Box 1)
  - Farrell, James T. "Youth" (Box 1)
  - Miller, George E. (Box 1)
  - Myrdal, Gunner
    - Correspondence (Box 1)
    - Writings, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Robinson, Alexander (Box 1)
- Teaching
  The arrangement of this series is Stensland's own. In a few cases the folders do not follow an obvious logical order, such as chronological or alphabetical. However, each subseries has its own structure.
  - Adult Education Centre, Fort William, Newfoundland
    - Course materials, 1945; includes Foundations of Adult Education, Sociology of the Community, and Discussion Techniques (Oversize 13)
    - Sociology, general materials (Oversize 13)
  - Kansas State College [KA]
    - Community development teaching materials, 1948-1952 (Box 2)
    - Institute of Citizenship, description of the "extension program" of the Institute (Box 2)
    - Publications and papers by PGS and others (Box 2)
    - Final Report on the Institute of Citizenship, 1945-1953 (Box 2)
    - "Land-Water-People" [work kit], 1951; for discussion group (Box 2)
    - Seminar in Educational Sociology, 1954; syllabus, writings, teaching materials (Box 2)
    - Missouri Valley Conference, 1949 (Box 2)
    - Kansas Commission for UNESCO, 1948-1953; Reports, publications, correspondence (Box 2)
  - Texas Technological College [TX]
    - The West Texas Regional Program in Adult Education
      - "The First Year" (report), 1952-1953 (Box 2)
      - "The Second Year" (report), 1953-1954 (Box 2)
      - Adult education, reports and studies, 1953 (Box 2)
      - "West Texas Regional Program" by PGS in Texas Libraries, 1953 (Box 2)
      - Thirteenth Quarterly Summary Report, Dec 1956; memorandum, newsletters; writings re Program in Adult Education (Box 2)
      - West Texas Regional Project on Adult Education, 1953 (Box 2)
      - Workshops, 1956-1957 (Box 2)
    - Regional Conferences and Projects
      - The First Midwinter Forum on Community Development, Jan 1954 (Box 2)
      - The Second Midwinter Forum on Community Development, Jan 1955 (Box 2)
      - Seybold Guest Ranch Conference, Sep 1956 (Box 2)
    - Teaching Materials
      - Adult Education, 1953; syllabus bound with student papers (Box 2)
      - Seminar in Educational Sociology, 1954; syllabus bound with student papers; misc materials; 2 folders (Box 2)
      - Ideas on Leadership, 1954; syllabus bound with student papers (Box 2)
    - "The Crisis" Statements (Box 3)
      Correspondence, documents, clippings related to the Board of Directors of Texas Tech dismissal of several professors and the disbanding of the Adult Education program.
  - Sardinia Project, European Productivity Agency (EPA) for the European Economic Cooperation (OECC) [SAR], ca 1958
    - Reports (Box 3)
    - European Seminar on Social Research and Community Development in European Problem Areas, Polarmo, Sicily, Jun 1958
      - Seminar papers; program information (Box 3)
      - Seminar papers, 2 folders (Oversize 13)
    - Community Development Conference, Tripoli, 1958 (Box 3)
  - University of Saskatchewan, Center for Community Studies [SASK]
    - Reports from clinics and workshops
      - Reports, 1960-1961 (Box 3)
      - Local Government Continuing Committee report, 1961 (Box 3)
    - Institute on Community Education for Health, Proceedings, 1961 (Box 3)
    - Community development, 1962; university program notes (Box 3)
    - Saskatchewan Assoc for Adult Education, 1963-1966; conference reports and papers (Box 3)
    - Second Conference on Education for General Practice, 1963 (Box 3)
    - Toronto Psychiatric Hospital Planning Conference, 1964 (Box 3)
    - Saskatchewan Registered Nurses' Assoc Conf, 1966 (Box 3)
    - Second Western Conference on Medical Education, 1966; interdisciplinary teaching (Box 3)
    - Staff Conference, 1966 (Oversize 1, Box 3)
    - Adult education overview, 1960's (Box 3)
    - Key to Community, Nos 2-5, 1966-1968 (Box 3)
    - Radio forum program, 1963 (Box 3)
  - Milbank Memorial Fund [MIL]
    These materials are arranged in the order that they were found.
    - Annual reports, 1967-1972 (Box 3)
    - Diaries, 1968 (Box 3)
    - Sixth Anniversary Conference, New York City (NYC), 1965 (Box 3)
    - Travel
      - Education Seminar of Faculty Fellows (Box 3)
      - CEMIC, Buenos Aires, Jan 1966 (Box 3)
      - Bogota meeting, Aug 1966 (Box 3)
      - Vina del Mar, Chile, Seminar on Teaching of "Medicinia Integrada", Jan 1968 (Box 3)
      - West Indies Eastern Caribbean Health Study Seminar, 1968 (Box 3)
      - UK/Yugoslav Seminar on Comparability in Health Services, Sep 1969 (Box 3)
      - UK/Yugoslav Seminar, organizing materials (Box 3)
      - UK/Yugoslav Seminar (Box 3)
      - UK and Scotland, interview summaries (Box 3)
      - NYC Seminar on Relationships Between Providers of Health Service and the Community, Apr 1969 (Box 3)
      - NYC Seminar
        - Printed materials (Box 3)
        - Seminar notes, 1969 (Box 3)
      - Brasilian Seminar, Jun 1970 (Box 3)
      - Mexico City, 1972; 3 folders (Box 3)
      - South America, 1970; 1972; interviews, notes, printed materials (Box 3)
      - Concepcion; Bogota, Santiago, Sao Paulo, Campinas, Campinas; III Conferencia Panamericana de Education Medica; Buenos Aires, ca 1970 (Box 3)
      - Reports on meetings and interviews, 1969-1970 (Box 3)
      - Aberdeen, Edinburgh, Birmingham, London, 1966 (Oversize 13)
      - Charlottesville, Nashville, New Orleans, May 1970 (Box 4)
      - Washington, DC (Box 4)
      - Miller, George; Hilliard, Jason, 1970; memos and correspondence (Box 4)
      - Sweden, 1971 (Box 4)
    - Conferences and Seminars
      - Fertility and Family planning in Latin America, 1967 (Box 4)
      - Health Services Research Seminar, 1969; includes writings of John Williamson (Box 4)
      - Reorientacion de la Educacion Medica en Colombia, 1970; materials, "teaching and learning"; 3 folders (Box 4)
      - Fourth World Conference on Medical Education, 1972 (Box 4)
      - Canadian Public Health Assoc, 63rd annual meeting, 1972 (Box 4)
      - IV Meeting of the Health Sciences Educations Information Center (HSEIC), Washington, DC, 1973 (Box 4)
      - Behavioral Sciences and Medical Education Conference
        - First, 1969; correspondence and proceedings (Box 4)
        - Third [canceled], 1970 (Box 4)
        - Fifth, 1971 (Box 4)
        - Sixth, 1972 (Box 4)
      - Conference on Research in Poverty and Development, 1968 (Box 4)
      - Gantt charts related to seminar planning (Box 14)
        See also Miscellaneous: Table (matrix) related to project or seminar planning
    - Miscellaneous
      - Herman San Martin, ca 1967 (Oversize 13)
      - Correspondence, 1969-1974; notes (Box 4)
      - Correspondence, medical, 1970-1974 (Box 4)
      - Correspondence, 1972; 1973 (Box 4)
      - References, publications; research paper (Box 4)
      - Milbank Fund publications, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Teacher's College, Columbia University [TC], 1973-1975
    - Continuing Professional Educational Seminar [CPA], 1974
      - Effective Approaches to Continuing Professional Education (Box 4)
      - Master copy of proposal for CPE Seminar, 1974 (Box 4)
      - Resources (Box 4)
      - General (Box 4)
      - Bibliography (Box 4)
      - Background statistics (Box 4)
      - Define what is adult education (Box 4)
      - Aims (Box 4)
      - Bibliography, 1974 (Box 4)
      - Outline, registration and grades (Box 4)
      - Reference and bibliography (Box 4)
      - AV - media (Box 4)
      - Introduction, pre-course planning (Box 4)
      - Teaching II, 9-10 (Box 4)
      - The physician II, 11-12 (Box 4)
      - Business, 13-14; law, 13-14 (Box 4)
      - Self-inventory (Box 4)
      - Medicine, II D (Box 4)
      - Law, II A (Box 4)
      - Synthesis, 15-16 (Box 4)
      - Engineer, 17-18, II C (Box 4)
      - Health professionals, offprints, journals and reports (Box 4)
    - Adult Education Courses [AEC]
      - Course outlines (Box 4)
      - Seminar notes [printed for distribution] (Box 4)
      - Bibliographies (Box 4)
      - Additional materials, notes, writing, printed materials; 2 folders (Box 4)
      - General aims (Box 5)
      - Strategies and roles (Box 5)
      - Setting goals; selecting content; choosing method (Box 5)
      - Definitions and philosophy (Box 5)
      - Agencies (Box 5)
      - The learner, additional materials (Box 5)
      - Attitude; general change (Box 5)
      - Case study, Morningside Heights (Box 5)
      - Learning, overall theories (Box 5)
      - Learning, misc notes (Box 5)
      - Research and learning (Box 5)
      - The learner [part II] (Box 5)
      - Teaching personnel, course listing (Box 5)
      - Contemporary Adult Education (goals and origins) (Box 5)
      - Research (Box 5)
      - University research, other research (Box 5)
      - ICAE, research participants and project (Box 5)
        See also Professional: International Council for Adult Education [ICAE]
      - Research on change (Box 5)
      - Research, preliminary outlines, proposal (Box 5)
      - Burke, May 20-21, 1975? (Box 5)
      - Commission on Professions of Adult Education (CPAE) (Box 5)
      - First person learning (Box 5)
    - Community development courses [CD]
      - Miscellaneous papers for community development (Box 5)
      - Teacher education (Box 5)
      - Planning phases (Box 5)
      - Discussion group material (Box 5)
      - Course evaluation (Box 5)
      - Outlines; outline for TD 6691 (Box 5)
      - Assignments and notes (Box 5)
      - Introduction (TD 300); bibliography (TD 3300), 1973 (Box 5)
      - Materials (TD 3300), 2 folders (Box 5)
    - Program planning [PP]
      - Program planning materials (Box 5)
      - NASA (Box 5)
      - Parameter (Box 5)
      - Forms (Box 5)
      - General background (Box 5)
      - Summary (Box 5)
      - Bibliography (Box 5)
      - Outlines (Box 5)
      - Grades; participants (Box 5)
      - Registration (TD 5601), 1975 (Box 5)
      - Papers, general (Box 5)
      - Workshop (Box 5)
      - Continuing education, nurses, 1974 (Box 5)
      - Communication and consultation (Box 5)
      - Health Careers Education (Box 5)
    - Old research, change potential, 1973 (Box 5)
    - Module Teaching Strategies [MTS], 1976
      This subseries contains teaching materials for "Teaching Strategies and Techniques," taught by PGS summer 1975. Included are both a typescript and xerox copy of a his book [?] Teaching Strategies and Techniques.
      - Teaching Strategies and Techniques by PGS, undated (Box 5)
      - Modules #1 - 8, "teaching" or "session" notes (printed materials) (Box 5)
      - Modules #9-10, "session" notes (printed materials) (Box 5)
      - Project management chart, teaching material graphic [marker on newsprint], 9 sheets (Box 14)
      - I - evaluation I; II:A - session 5; II:B - session 6; II:C&D - session 7-8 (evaluation II); III:A&B - session 8-9 [original folder empty]; III:C&D - evaluation III (Box 5)
      - Module, overheads and notes (Box 6)
      - Module I:A (Box 6)
      - Strategy two; strategy three (Box 6)
      - Strategy four; strategy five (Box 6)
      - Student evaluations (Box 6)
      - Module, extra items (Box 6)
      - Final plans for demonstration (Box 6)
      - Strategy IV ratings and presentations (Box 6)
      - Class sessions 1 - 4 (class TO 5601) (Box 6)
    - Miscellaneous
      - "Continuing Education Needs of Directors of Hospital Nursing Inservice Education in New York State." [Dissertation], 1975
  - Hunter College, New York City [HC], 1974
    - Institute of Health Science [IHT] (Box 6)
      - Summary of course, "Basic Concepts of Public Health and Health Care" (Box 6)
      - Syllabus; bibliography; basic concepts (Box 6)
      - Outlines (Box 6)
      - Materials (Box 6)
      - Evaluations and exams (Box 6)
      - Notes, 2 folders (Box 6)
      - Handouts (Box 6)
      - International (Box 6)
      - Professional and health planning (materials), 8 folders (Box 6)
      - Professional and health planning (oversize materials) (Oversize 13)
  - New York University [NYU], 1975-1976
    - Sweden / Scotland Seminar, 1976
      - Scotland (Box 6)
      - Budget (Box 6)
      - Sweden (Box 6)
      - Sweden, printed materials, 2 folders (Box 6, 7)
    - Center for International Health Education [CIHE]
      - Notes (Box 7)
      - Correspondence (Box 7)
      - Center proposal, 1st draft with notes on discussion (Box 7)
      - Application, 3rd draft (Box 7)
      - Center application (Box 7)
      - Center application, appendix (Box 7)
      - Proposal, corrections (Box 7)
      - Proposal, corrected copy (Box 7)
      - Fellowship applications, These three files are the same as "Center application files" listed above; 3 folders (Box 7)
      - Advisory committee, 2 folders (Box 7)
      - Contacts; information (Box 7)
      - Correspondence (Box 7)
      - Project comments (Box 7)
      - Timing of Center proposal, suggested (Box 7)
      - Medical center (Box 7)
      - Resources (Box 7)
      - Grant proposal (I) (Box 7)
      - Seminar report, 1976 (Box 7)
      - Curriculum and course descriptions for international community health education (Box 7)
      - International Internship in Community Health Education project, 1975 (Box 7)
      - NDEA-Title VI (Language Development Act) meeting, 1976 (Box 7)
  - University of Toronto [UT]
    - Comparative Studies in Adult Education [CSAE], 1977
      - Unit I, II & III, notes (Box 7)
      - Unit I, origins, 2 folders (Box 7)
      - Phase I, materials; phase II (Box 7)
      - Unit II, approaches to learning (Box 7)
      - Unit II, theory of learning & summary (Box 7)
      - Unit III, strategies (Box 7)
      - Unit IV, role of education (Box 7)
      - Methods (teaching), teaching materials, offprints, notes (Box 7)
      - Activities (general outline), teaching materials (Box 7)
      - Field trip (July) (Box 7)
      - Philosophy, international examples (Box 7)
      - Comparatives studies and reports (Box 7)
      - University and college education (Box 7)
      - Papers, newsletters (Box 7)
      - University extension administration charts (Box 7)
      - University programs (Box 7)
      - Background (class 4600 A:3) (Box 7)
      - "C" (Box 7)
      - [Education] 1114, general materials, 1977; 2 folders (Box 7)
      - Bibliographies (Box 7)
  - International Conference on Primary Health Care, Alma Ata, Russia [AA], 1978; Stensland was the representative from International Council for Adult Education [ICAE].
    - Health Project Materials
      - Health Care 1976, country program, printed reports (Box 7)
      - Latin America, printed materials; 3 folders (Box 7, 8)
      - Eastern Mediterranean Region (EMRO), printed materials (II) (Box 8)
      - Yemen Arab Republic, reports (Oversize 13)
      - Asia (I), printed materials (Box 8)
      - Western Pacific, printed materials (Box 8)
      - Africa, 2 folders; printed materials (Box 8)
      - Europe, printed materials (Box 8)
      - United Nations, printed materials (Box 8)
      - American Public Health Association [APHA] authors and vouchers, correspondence (Box 8)
      - APHA correspondence (Box 8)
      - Conference material; APHA post-conference meeting (Box 8)
      - Health Research plans (Box 8)
      - Notes (Box 8)
      - Journals, 3 folders (Box 8)
      - Reports (Box 8)
      - Reports - WHO, 2 folders (Box 8)
      - Publication - WHO (Box 8)
      - Reports by Country
        - Reports, international (Box 8)
        - Sanitary (Box 9)
        - World Health Organization (Box 9)
  - Personalized Care Model Training Project [PCM], 1980
    - Regional Research Council of American, general information; correspondence (Box 9)
    - PCM, 4 folders (Box 9)
    - Special materials (Box 9)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Teaching materials, 2 folders (Box 9)
    - Slang; words; communication channels (Box 9)
- Professional
  - International Council for Adult Education [ICAE]
    See also Teacher's College, Columbia University: Adult Education Courses: ICAE, research participants and project
    - Continuing Professional Education, 1977; proposal (in a binder of materials from J.R. Kidd) (Box 9)
    - Correspondence; newsletter, publications, 1980-1983 (Box 9)
    - General materials, newsletter; offprint (Box 9)
    - Correspondence
      - Buttedhal, Paz, 1977 (Box 9)
      - Gayfer, Margaret, 1977-1980; women's rights (Box 9)
      - Hall, Budd - Participatory Research Project, 1976-1981 (Box 9)
      - Kidd, J.R., 1974-1981 (Box 9)
      - Miller, Paul, 1976-1978 (Box 9)
      - Thomas, Dorothy, 1976-1979 (Box 9)
      - General; ICAE questionnaire, 1977-1980 (Box 9)
    - Publications (Box 9)
    - Finance and expenses [personal and organizational], 1976-1980 (Box 9)
    - Seminar on Adult Education and Development, Kungalv Sweden, 1979; correspondence; documents (Box 9)
    - Gothenburg lectures: "Health in a Changing Environment", 1977; 2 folders (Box 9)
    - Nordic trip report, Sept-Oct 1977 (Box 9)
    - Zambia workshop, 1977 (Box 9)
    - Dar Es Salaam, 1976 (Oversize 13)
    - Primary Care and Education for Development [collaboration of ICAE, WHO and UNICEF, and others], ca 1978; proposal; correspondence; reports (Box 9)
    - Primary Health Care workshop (Box 9)
    - Office of Education, U.S., correspondence (Box 9)
- Consultations
  - World Bank/World Education, 1977-1978
    - General (Box 9)
    - Saudi Arabia (Box 9)
    - World Education report, 1977 (Box 9)
    - Correspondence; memorandum; reports (Box 9)
  - Adult Learning Services
    - Norman Kurland [New York State Education Dept], 1977-1979; reports; papers; correspondence (Box 9)
  - Kellogg
    - Consultation, National Fellowship Program, 1977-1979; correspondence and reports (Box 9)
    - Correspondence, conferences, 1981; letters to Congress re health care funding; conference folder for Alpha Center for Health Planning (Box 9)
- Conferences, Workshops and Seminars
  Included here is a series of folders located together without a general title by Stensland. It is not clear what Stensland's role was in any of these conferences.
  See also International Conference on Primary Health Care, Alma Ata, Russia [AA] 1978
  - Leadership Training, Chautaugua Institute, 1953 (Box 9)
  - Introduction to Mid-Management Seminar, ca 1953 (Box 9)
  - Local Government Continuing Committee, Saskatchewan, Canada, 1960; training program for local government (Box 9)
  - Arctic Research Laboratory, Point Barrow, Alaska, 1962 (Box 10)
  - Education for Leisure, 1965 (Box 10)
  - Federacion Panamericana de Asociaciones de Facultades de Medicina, Bogota, 1973 (Box 10)
  - Conference on the Professions, University of the State of New York, 1977 (Box 10)
  - Proceedings (Box 10)
  - Fund for Adult Education, undated (Box 10)
- Community Development
  Included here are papers written by Stensland or other authors, some of which were used as teaching materials. The contents of some files are redundant of materials found elsewhere in the collection. This series is rich in teaching materials and documentation of Stensland's approach to community development and the teaching process itself.
  Material on community development is also scattered throughout the collection under various topics.
  - Theory research, Kansas, Saskatchewan, Texas
    - Theory and parameters (Box 10)
    - Goals of adult education (Box 10)
    - Values; evaluation (Box 10)
- Speeches